<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jared Clark</title>
    <link>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jared Clark</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 11:36:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jaredclark0626.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing App Service Delivery Azure CDN</title>
      <link>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/posts/optimizing-app-service-delivery-azurecdn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 11:36:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/posts/optimizing-app-service-delivery-azurecdn/</guid>
      <description>tags:
 App Service Plans App Service Azure Optimizing   Short-hand:
  Azure CDN - Azure Content Delivery Network
  AS - App Service
  ASP - App Service Plan
  Optimizing App Service using Azure CDN
In this short blog we will talk about optimizing the content delivery to an App Service using Azure Content Delivery Network. This will help us delivery updated versions of our code to Azure CDN to different regions around the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Up and Down App Service Plans</title>
      <link>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/posts/scaling-up-and-down-app-service-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 08:32:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/posts/scaling-up-and-down-app-service-plans/</guid>
      <description>Short-hand:
 ASE - App Service Environment  This will be a short blog since I will be only giving a brief overview of scaling up and down App Service plans. We will talk about how to scale up and down app service plans manually and automate scaling depending on workload. First, I want to give you a general overview of scaling up and down app services.
Overview of Scaling Up and Down App Service Plans</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating and deploying Microsoft Azure App Service Plan</title>
      <link>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/posts/managing-microsoft-azure-app-service-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 10:02:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/posts/managing-microsoft-azure-app-service-plan/</guid>
      <description>Short-hand:
 Azure DevOps - ADO Continuous Deployment - CD Continuous Integration - CI VS - Visual Studio  In this blog I will give you an overview of Microsoft App Service plans, how to create and app Service Plan and finally how to create an App Service. We will talk about options on how to deploy code to App Services. To kick this off let me give you an overview of Microsoft App Service Plan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaredclark0626.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Jared Clark
From: Cleveland, Ohio
Lives: Charlotte, North Carolina
Background:
I am an effective software technician with proven experience in my current and past positions. I have utilized my education, technical training, and employment training to enhance my knowledge and skills. I desire a position with an organization that can best utilize my background and knowledge to exceed its company’s vision and goals.
Hobbies:
Certifications:
 Azure DevOps Assessment (18473) Learn System Center 2016: Virtual Machine Manager AWS-Solution Architect Associate Certification from Cert-School  Accomplishments:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>